{
    "name": "Modern History of Assam (1826 to 1947) Colonial Assam (1826-1947)",
    "questions": [
        {
            "question": "In which year the British Crown invaded Assam?",
            "options": [
                "A. 1857",
                "B. 1859",
                "C. 1826",
                "D. 1860"
            ],
            "answer": "C. 1826"
        },
        {
            "question": "In which year the treaty of Yandaboo was signed?",
            "options": [
                "A. 1826, 24th Feb",
                "B. 1857, 24th Feb",
                "C. 1885, 24th Feb",
                "D. 1824, 24th Feb"
            ],
            "answer": "A. 1826, 24th Feb"
        },
        {
            "question": "Yandabo Treaty was signed between East India company and the",
            "options": [
                "A. Ahom King",
                "B. King of Burma",
                "C. Kachari King",
                "D. Chutiya King"
            ],
            "answer": "B. King of Burma"
        },
        {
            "question": "Who was the monarch of Burma at the time of Yandabo Treaty?",
            "options": [
                "A. Bagyidaw",
                "B. Sagaing Min",
                "C. Tharrawaddy Min",
                "D. Bodawpaya"
            ],
            "answer": "B. Sagaing Min"
        },
        {
            "question": "Who among the following signed the Treaty of Yandaboo, on behalf of the East India Company?",
            "options": [
                "A. Major - General Sir Archibald Campbell",
                "B. Captain Welsh",
                "C. Captain Norton",
                "D. David Scott"
            ],
            "answer": "A. Major - General Sir Archibald Campbell"
        },
        {
            "question": "Yandabo Treaty was signed by:",
            "options": [
                "A. Archibald Campbell and Bagyidaw",
                "B. Archibald Campbell and Maha Min Hla Kyaw Htin",
                "C. Arthur Richards and Bagyidaw",
                "D. None of these"
            ],
            "answer": "B. Archibald Campbell and Maha Min Hla Kyaw Htin"
        },
        {
            "question": "As per Yandabo Treaty which of the following is correct?",
            "options": [
                "A. Assam, Manipur, Arakan, were ceded to British",
                "B. Burmese decided to allow diplomatic ambassadors from British",
                "C. Only A is correct",
                "D. Both A and B are correct"
            ],
            "answer": "D. Both A and B are correct"
        },
        {
            "question": "When did the British annex Assam?",
            "options": [
                "A. 1772",
                "B. 1786",
                "C. 1805",
                "D. 1826"
            ],
            "answer": "D. 1826"
        },
        {
            "question": "Who was the first British Commissioner of Assam?",
            "options": [
                "A. David Scott",
                "B. John Howard",
                "C. William Cooke",
                "D. David Lyne"
            ],
            "answer": "A. David Scott"
        },
        {
            "question": "Which one is INCORRECT about the undivided Goalpara district?",
            "options": [
                "A. The region came under the control of East India Company in the year 1765.",
                "B. Under the East Indian Company rule, the area was under Rangpur Administration.",
                "C. The area was renamed as 'North- Eastern Parts of Rangpur' before the Yandabo Treaty.",
                "D. North Eastern Rangpur was constituted as Goalpara district in the year 1947."
            ],
            "answer": "D. North Eastern Rangpur was constituted as Goalpara district in the year 1947."
        },
        {
            "question": "Which of the following district was NOT a part of the ancient undivided Kamrup district?",
            "options": [
                "A. Goalpara",
                "B. Nalbari",
                "C. Barpeta",
                "D. John Howard"
            ],
            "answer": "A. Goalpara"
        },
        {
            "question": "Who was the first Chief Commissioner of Assam?",
            "options": [
                "A. Archdale Earle",
                "B. Sir Nicholas Dodd Beatson Bell",
                "C. Sir William Sinclair Marris",
                "D. None of these"
            ],
            "answer": "A. Archdale Earle"
        },
        {
            "question": "When was the first rebellion in Assam against the British Rule held?",
            "options": [
                "A. 1812",
                "B. 1828",
                "C. 1836",
                "D. 1882"
            ],
            "answer": "B. 1828"
        },
        {
            "question": "Who was the first Assamese to fight against British?",
            "options": [
                "A. Kushal Knowar",
                "B. Piyoli Phukan",
                "C. Maniram Dewan",
                "D. Gomdhar Konwar"
            ],
            "answer": "D. Gomdhar Konwar"
        },
        {
            "question": "The first rebellion against the British Rule in Assam in 1828 was led by",
            "options": [
                "A. Piyali Phukan",
                "B. Piyali Baruah",
                "C. Gomadhar Konwar",
                "D. Maniram Dewan"
            ],
            "answer": "C. Gomadhar Konwar"
        },
        {
            "question": "In which of the following year Lower Assam was permanently annexed by the British?",
            "options": [
                "A. 1826 A.D",
                "B. 1828 A.D",
                "C. 1830 A.D",
                "D. 1845 A.D"
            ],
            "answer": "B. 1828 A.D"
        },
        {
            "question": "In which year the Kachari kingdom was annexed by British?",
            "options": [
                "A. 1826",
                "B. 1828",
                "C. 1832",
                "D. 1838"
            ],
            "answer": "B. 1828"
        },
        {
            "question": "In 1828, Kachari kingdom was annexed under which of the following doctrine?",
            "options": [
                "A. Doctrine of Lapse",
                "B. Doctrine of Administrative law",
                "C. Doctrine of Laches",
                "D. None of these"
            ],
            "answer": "C. Doctrine of Lapse"
        },
        {
            "question": "Who was the ruler of North Cachar before the annexation of the British?",
            "options": [
                "A. Gobinda Chandra Narayan",
                "B. Krishnachandra Narayan",
                "C. Tularam Senapaty",
                "D. None of these"
            ],
            "answer": "C. Tularam Senapaty"
        },
        {
            "question": "The first Khasi chief to declare war against the British was:",
            "options": [
                "A. Tirot Singh",
                "B. Bir Singha",
                "C. Hari Singh",
                "D. Birendra Singha"
            ],
            "answer": "A. Tirot Singh"
        },
        {
            "question": "In 1830, who among the following attempted to organise a confederacy of Assam tribes in order to wrest back the country from the hands of East-India Company?",
            "options": [
                "A. Koncheng Bar patra Gohain",
                "B. Atan Buragohain",
                "C. Piali Barphukan",
                "D. Laluk Barphukan"
            ],
            "answer": "C. Piali Barphukan"
        },
        {
            "question": "In which year Dhananjoy Burhagohain, Piyali Phukan and Jiuram Medhi rose a revolt against British occupation in Assam?",
            "options": [
                "A. 1830",
                "B. 1832",
                "C. 1835",
                "D. 1857"
            ],
            "answer": "A. 1830"
        },
        {
            "question": "Piyali Phukan was hanged in the year",
            "options": [
                "A. June 25, 1830",
                "B. July 26, 1830",
                "C. August 26, 1830",
                "D. August 25, 1830"
            ],
            "answer": "B. July 26, 1830"
        },
        {
            "question": "The year 1836 was crucial in case of Assamese language & literature because:",
            "options": [
                "A. Bengali Language was imposed over Assamese as the British took over Assam.",
                "B. Assamese novels were translated to English for the first time.",
                "C. Assam Sahitya Sabha was formed.",
                "D. Oronodoi was published."
            ],
            "answer": "A. Bengali Language was imposed over Assamese as the British took over Assam."
        },
        {
            "question": "Cachar was placed under the Commissionerate of Dacca in",
            "options": [
                "A. 1836",
                "B. 1837",
                "C. 1839",
                "D. 1840"
            ],
            "answer": "A. 1836"
        },
        {
            "question": "When was the first tea garden established in India?",
            "options": [
                "A. 1834",
                "B. 1835",
                "C. 1837",
                "D. 1840"
            ],
            "answer": "C. 1837"
        },
        {
            "question": "Where was the first Tea garden established in India?",
            "options": [
                "A. Namrup, Dibrugarh",
                "B. Chabua, Dibrugarh",
                "C. Sonari, Charaideo",
                "D. Margherita, Tinsukia"
            ],
            "answer": "B. Chabua, Dibrugarh"
        },
        {
            "question": "Upper Assam was annexed to British Empire in the year",
            "options": [
                "A. 1826",
                "B. 1837",
                "C. 1838",
                "D. 1842"
            ],
            "answer": "C. 1838"
        },
        {
            "question": "When was the Assam Tea company established?",
            "options": [
                "A. 1826",
                "B. 1830",
                "C. 1835",
                "D. 1839"
            ],
            "answer": "D. 1839"
        },
        {
            "question": "Who was called the first tea planter of Assam?",
            "options": [
                "A. Maniram Dewan",
                "B. Nicholas Dodd Beatson Bell",
                "C. Gomdhar Konwar",
                "D. Hōne Heke"
            ],
            "answer": "A. Maniram Dewan"
        },
        {
            "question": "Who was the first Indian to grow tea commercially?",
            "options": [
                "A. Piyali Barua",
                "B. Purnananda Buragohain",
                "C. Maniram Dewan",
                "D. None of these"
            ],
            "answer": "C. Maniram Dewan"
        },
        {
            "question": "When did the Assam Tea Company begin its commercial production?",
            "options": [
                "A. 1837",
                "B. 1839",
                "C. 1840",
                "D. 1845"
            ],
            "answer": "C. 1840"
        },
        {
            "question": "Which one is CORRECT about the tea production in Assam during the Colonial period of Assam?",
            "options": [
                "A. First tea garden was established in Assam in 1858.",
                "B. Assam Tea Company began commercial production in 1858.",
                "C. First Tea garden was established in Chabua, Dibrugarh.",
                "D. All of these."
            ],
            "answer": "C. First Tea garden was established in Chabua, Dibrugarh\n(First tea garden was established in 1837 and the Assam Tea Company began commercial production in 1840)"
        },
        {
            "question": "When was the region of Matak & Sadiya annexed by British?",
            "options": [
                "A. 1826",
                "B. 1828",
                "C. 1839",
                "D. 1842"
            ],
            "answer": "D. 1842"
        },
        {
            "question": "The first Assamese periodical was first published by American Baptist Missionaries in the year",
            "options": [
                "A. 1886",
                "B. 1846",
                "C. 1885",
                "D. 1871"
            ],
            "answer": "B. 1846"
        },
        {
            "question": "The first Assamese magazine Orunodoi was published in the year",
            "options": [
                "A. 1836",
                "B. 1846",
                "C. 1872",
                "D. 1882"
            ],
            "answer": "B. 1846"
        },
        {
            "question": "The Association ―Gyan Pradayini Sabha‖ was initiated by-",
            "options": [
                "A. Anandaram Dhekial Phukan and Gunabhiram Barua",
                "B. Anandaram Dhekial Phukan and Devicharan Barua",
                "C. Jagannath Barua and Gunabhiram Barua",
                "D. Jagannath Barua and Manik Chandra Barooah."
            ],
            "answer": "A. Anandaram Dhekial Phukan and Gunabhiram Baruah"
        },
        {
            "question": "Who among the following was sent to Andaman for the plan to bring Kandarpeswar to the throne?",
            "options": [
                "A. Sheikh Formud Ali",
                "B. Kamala Baruah",
                "C. Bahadur Gaon Burha",
                "D. Both A & C"
            ],
            "answer": "D. Both A & C"
        },
        {
            "question": "In Assam the period from 1826 to 1858 CE is known as:",
            "options": [
                "A. British Rule",
                "B. Manor Din",
                "C. Company Raj",
                "D. Government Rule"
            ],
            "answer": "C. Company Raj"
        },
        {
            "question": "Which of the following Act transferred power from the English East India Company to the British Crown?",
            "options": [
                "A. The Government of India Act 1858",
                "B. Government of Indian Act 1919",
                "C. Indian Council Act 1861",
                "D. Government of India Act 1935"
            ],
            "answer": "A. The Government of India Act 1858"
        },
        {
            "question": "Who was the leader of the 1857 revolt in Assam?",
            "options": [
                "A. Lachit Barphukan",
                "B. Pioli Baruah",
                "C. Maniram Dewan",
                "D. Kanaklata"
            ],
            "answer": "C. Maniram Dewan"
        },
        {
            "question": "Subedar Sheikh Bhikun and Subedar Nur Mahammad is known for:",
            "options": [
                "A. Leading the Sepoy Mutiny in Assam",
                "B. Joining the conspiracy to bring Kandarpeswar to the throne.",
                "C. Revolting against the annexation of Sylhet to Chief Commissioner's province of Assam",
                "D. None of these"
            ],
            "answer": "B. Joining the conspiracy to bring Kandarpeswar to the throne."
        },
        {
            "question": "Who was popular among the people of Upper Assam as ‗Kalita Raja‘?",
            "options": [
                "A. Lachit Barphukan",
                "B. Pioli Baruah",
                "C. Maniram Dewan",
                "D. Kanaklata"
            ],
            "answer": "C. Maniram Dewan"
        },
        {
            "question": "When was Maniram Dewan publicly hanged for his involvement in the rebellion against the British?",
            "options": [
                "A. 20 Feb. 1857",
                "B. 26 Feb. 1858",
                "C. 28 Feb. 1859",
                "D. 1st March 1870"
            ],
            "answer": "B. 26 Feb. 1858"
        },
        {
            "question": "Who was hanged publicly with Maniram Dewan?",
            "options": [
                "A. Piyali Phukan",
                "B. Piyali Baruah",
                "C. Dutiram Barua",
                "D. None of these"
            ],
            "answer": "B. Piyali Baruah"
        },
        {
            "question": "Which of the following was the CORRECT reason for hanging Maniram Dewan?",
            "options": [
                "A. He was hanged because he was a leader of Sepoy-mutiny.",
                "B. He was identified as the kingpin of the plot to bring Kandarpeswar to the throne.",
                "C. He was the first India to grow tea commercially without British permission.",
                "D. None of these"
            ],
            "answer": "B. He was identified as the kingpin of the plot to bring Kandarpeswar to the throne."
        },
        {
            "question": "Which of the following is INCORRECT about Maniram Dewan",
            "options": [
                "A. Maniram Dewan was the first person to establish tea gardens in Assam.",
                "B. Maniram Dewan was a borbhandar (Prime Minister) of Purandar Singha.",
                "C. Maniram Dewan was the only martyr in India who was hanged during the phase of sepoy mutiny.",
                "D. Maniram Dewan was hanged by the British for conspiring against them during the 1857 uprising."
            ],
            "answer": "C. Maniram Dewan was the only martyr in India who was hanged during the phase of sepoy mutiny."
        },
        {
            "question": "Which one of the following sites is linked to the Sepoy Mutiny?",
            "options": [
                "A. Madan Kamdev",
                "B. Surya Pahar",
                "C. Northbrook Gate",
                "D. Malegarh Ruins"
            ],
            "answer": "C. Northbrook Gate"
        },
        {
            "question": "The waste land rule was passed under which one of the following commissioners?",
            "options": [
                "A. David Scott",
                "B. Thomas Campbell Robertson",
                "C. Francis Jenkins",
                "D. Henry Hopkinson"
            ],
            "answer": "C. Francis Jenkins"
        },
        {
            "question": "The first Peasant uprising in Assam against the British rule was?",
            "options": [
                "A. Phulaguri Dhawa",
                "B. Patharughat Raijmel",
                "C. Battle of Itakhuli",
                "D. Rangiya Raijmel"
            ],
            "answer": "A. Phulaguri Dhawa"
        },
        {
            "question": "India's first Peasant movement against the British rule was:",
            "options": [
                "A. Malabar rebellion",
                "B. Bardoli Satyagraha",
                "C. Phulaguri Dhawa",
                "D. Jorhat Raijmel"
            ],
            "answer": "C. Phulaguri Dhawa"
        },
        {
            "question": "The Phulaguri uprising took place in the year",
            "options": [
                "A. 1848",
                "B. 1852",
                "C. 1861",
                "D. 1869"
            ],
            "answer": "C. 1861"
        },
        {
            "question": "The reason behind the peasants of Nagaon gathered at Phulaguri for a raij mel (peoples' assembly) was:",
            "options": [
                "A. To protest against taxes on Tea",
                "B. To protest against taxes on Rice",
                "C. To protest against British Occupation",
                "D. To protest against taxes on Betel-nut and paan"
            ],
            "answer": "D. To protest against taxes on Betel-nut and paan (Tamul – Pan)"
        },
        {
            "question": "What was the name of the British officer who was killed during Phulaguri uprising?",
            "options": [
                "A. Lt. Dawson",
                "B. Lt. Robert",
                "C. Lt. Singer",
                "D. Lt. Brook"
            ],
            "answer": "C. Lt. Singer"
        },
        {
            "question": "The first oil well of Asia was drilled at",
            "options": [
                "A. Digboi",
                "B. Geleki",
                "C. Lakwa",
                "D. Naharkatia"
            ],
            "answer": "A. Digboi"
        },
        {
            "question": "The first oil well at Digboi was dug in the year",
            "options": [
                "A. 1866",
                "B. 1883",
                "C. 1889",
                "D. 1901"
            ],
            "answer": "A. 1866"
        },
        {
            "question": "In which year the first dictionary in Assamese language was publised",
            "options": [
                "A. 1861",
                "B. 1867",
                "C. 1901",
                "D. 1903"
            ],
            "answer": "B. 1867"
        },
        {
            "question": "Which of the following period is called \"The Dark Age of Assamese Language‖?",
            "options": [
                "A. 1826-1830",
                "B. 1830-1835",
                "C. 1836-1863",
                "D. 1836-1873"
            ],
            "answer": "D. 1836-1873"
        },
        {
            "question": "Assam became Chief Commissioner's Province in the year",
            "options": [
                "A. 1858",
                "B. 1874",
                "C. 1876",
                "D. 1857"
            ],
            "answer": "B. 1874"
        },
        {
            "question": "Assam was tagged with which province during the colonial rule?",
            "options": [
                "A. Bengal",
                "B. Bihar",
                "C. Sylhet",
                "D. North East"
            ],
            "answer": "C. Sylhet"
        },
        {
            "question": "When was Sylhet added to the Chief Commissioner's Province in Assam region?",
            "options": [
                "A. 1858",
                "B. 1874",
                "C. 1876",
                "D. 1857"
            ],
            "answer": "B. 1874"
        },
        {
            "question": "What was the capital of the Province ‗Eastern Bengal and Assam‘?",
            "options": [
                "A. Shillong",
                "B. Rangpur",
                "C. Chittagong",
                "D. Dacca"
            ],
            "answer": "D. Dacca"
        },
        {
            "question": "In which year Assam region was separated from Bengal territory and was put under a Chief Commissioner?",
            "options": [
                "A. 1856",
                "B. 1857",
                "C. 1858",
                "D. 1874"
            ],
            "answer": "D. 1874"
        },
        {
            "question": "Which of the following is the first political association of colonial Assam?",
            "options": [
                "A. Assam Chatra Sanmilan",
                "B. Sarbajanik Sabha of Jorhat",
                "C. Phulaguri Dhawa",
                "D. None of these"
            ],
            "answer": "B. Sarbajanik Sabha of Jorhat"
        },
        {
            "question": "The Jorhat Sarbajanik Sabha was founded in the year",
            "options": [
                "A. 1884",
                "B. 1885",
                "C. 1886",
                "D. 1889"
            ],
            "answer": "A. 1884"
        },
        {
            "question": "The Association which first created a stir against the British rule among the Assamese was the 'Jorhat Sarbajanik Sabha' which was founded by",
            "options": [
                "A. Jagannath Barooah",
                "B. Omeo Kumar Das",
                "C. Tarun Ram Phukan",
                "D. Pushpalata Das"
            ],
            "answer": "A. Jagannath Barooah"
        },
        {
            "question": "Who was the first Assamese to join the Indian National Congress during its second session held in 1886?",
            "options": [
                "A. Gopinath Bordoloi",
                "B. Tarunram Phukan",
                "C. Devicharan Baruah",
                "D. Nobin Chandra Bordoloi"
            ],
            "answer": "D. Nobin Chandra Bordoloi"
        },
        {
            "question": "In which year oil was discovered in Digboi?",
            "options": [
                "A. 1866",
                "B. 1883",
                "C. 1889",
                "D. 1901"
            ],
            "answer": "C. 1889"
        },
        {
            "question": "India (and Asia) obtained its first refinery in Digboi in the year",
            "options": [
                "A. 1866",
                "B. 1883",
                "C. 1889",
                "D. 1901"
            ],
            "answer": "D. 1901"
        },
        {
            "question": "When did the peasant revolt of Patharughat take place",
            "options": [
                "A. 28 January 1894",
                "B. 30 January 1890",
                "C. 1 January 1884",
                "D. 28 January 1794"
            ],
            "answer": "A. 28 January 1894"
        },
        {
            "question": "Where did the 'Patharughatar Ron' take place?",
            "options": [
                "A. Nagaon",
                "B. Sivasagar",
                "C. Goalpara",
                "D. Darrang"
            ],
            "answer": "D. Darrang"
        },
        {
            "question": "Patharughatar Ran or Battle of Patharughat was the consequence of:",
            "options": [
                "A. British Monopoly over opium trade",
                "B. Enhanced revenue collection by British through tax",
                "C. Usury by money lenders",
                "D. Against taxes on Betel-nut and paan"
            ],
            "answer": "B. Enhanced revenue collection by British through tax"
        },
        {
            "question": "Which of the following is known as Assam's Jallianwala Bagh massacre?",
            "options": [
                "A. Phulaguri Dhawa",
                "B. Patharughatar Ran",
                "C. Itakhuli Raij Mel",
                "D. Jorhat Sarvbajanik Sabha"
            ],
            "answer": "B. Patharughatar Ran"
        },
        {
            "question": "What was the precursor of Assam Sahitya Sabha?",
            "options": [
                "A. Asam Sahitya Sabha Patrika",
                "B. Sivasagar Zila Sahitya Sabha",
                "C. Assam Sanmilan",
                "D. Oxomiya Bhaxa Unnati Xadhini Xobha"
            ],
            "answer": "D. Oxomiya Bhaxa Unnati Xadhini Xobha"
        },
        {
            "question": "In which of the following year Oxomiya Bhaxa Unnati Xadhini Xobha was formed?",
            "options": [
                "A. 1889",
                "B. 1888",
                "C. 1887",
                "D. 1886"
            ],
            "answer": "B. 1888"
        },
        {
            "question": "Who was the first Secretary of 'Oxomiya Bhaxa Unnati Xadhini Xobha'?",
            "options": [
                "A. Kunjalal Sharma",
                "B. Jyoti Prasad Agarwala",
                "C. Sayed Abdul Malik",
                "D. Shivaram Sharma Bordoloi"
            ],
            "answer": "D. Shivaram Sharma Bordoloi"
        },
        {
            "question": "Which of following marked the dawn of Romanticism in Assamese literature?",
            "options": [
                "A. Orunodoi",
                "B. Prantik",
                "C. Jonaki",
                "D. Goriyoshi"
            ],
            "answer": "C. Jonaki"
        },
        {
            "question": "In which year Assamese magazine 'Jonaki' was first published?",
            "options": [
                "A. 1887",
                "B. 1889",
                "C. 1890",
                "D. 1896"
            ],
            "answer": "B. 1889"
        },
        {
            "question": "Who was the first editor of the Assamese magazine Jonaki?",
            "options": [
                "A. Lakshminath Bezbaruah",
                "B. Anandaram Dhekial Phukan",
                "C. Anandachandra Agarwala",
                "D. Chandrakumar Agarwala"
            ],
            "answer": "D. Chandrakumar Agarwala"
        },
        {
            "question": "In 1897, who translated the 'Bargaon copper-plate' of Ratna Pala?",
            "options": [
                "A. Dr. Hoemle",
                "B. Dr. S.K. Bhuyan",
                "C. E.G. Glazie",
                "D. M. Kosh"
            ],
            "answer": "A. Dr. Hoemle"
        },
        {
            "question": "Assam Association was formed in the year",
            "options": [
                "A. 1900",
                "B. 1903",
                "C. 1905",
                "D. 1910"
            ],
            "answer": "B. 1903"
        },
        {
            "question": "Who formed Assam Association / who was the first secretary of Assam Association?",
            "options": [
                "A. Gopinath Bordoloi",
                "B. Raja Prabhat Chandra Baruah",
                "C. Jagannath Baruah",
                "D. Manik Chandra Baruah"
            ],
            "answer": "D. Manik Chandra Baruah"
        },
        {
            "question": "Who was the first elected president of the Assam Association?",
            "options": [
                "A. Gopinath Bordoloi",
                "B. Raja Prabhat Chandra Baruah",
                "C. Jagannath Baruah",
                "D. Manik Chandra Baruah"
            ],
            "answer": "B. Raja Prabhat Chandra Baruah"
        },
        {
            "question": "Where did the first session of the Assam Association held?",
            "options": [
                "A. Guwahati",
                "B. Jorhat",
                "C. Dibrugarh",
                "D. Tezpur"
            ],
            "answer": "C. Dibrugarh"
        },
        {
            "question": "Which one is INCORRECT about the Assam Association?",
            "options": [
                "A. It was formed in 1903.",
                "B. First session of the Assam Association was held in Dibrugarh in 1905.",
                "C. Assam Association was merged with Assam Pradesh Congress Committee in 1921.",
                "D. Gopinath Bordoloi was the founding president of Assam Association"
            ],
            "answer": "D. Gopinath Bordoloi was the founding president of Assam Association."
        },
        {
            "question": "From which of the following event, peasants from East Bengal began settling down in the riverine tracts (char) of the Brahmaputra valley as encouraged by the British to increase agricultural production?",
            "options": [
                "A. Swadeshi Movement (1918-1947)",
                "B. Partition of Bengal (1905)",
                "C. When Bengali was replaced as the official language in 1937",
                "D. None of these"
            ],
            "answer": "B. Partition of Bengal (1905)"
        },
        {
            "question": "In 1905, the Swadeshi Movement in Assam was led by",
            "options": [
                "A. Gopinath Bordoloi",
                "B. Tarun Ram Phukan",
                "C. Bishnu Prasad Rabha",
                "D. Ambikagiri Raychoudhury"
            ],
            "answer": "D. Ambikagiri Raychoudhury"
        },
        {
            "question": "The Assam Association was replaced with the name of",
            "options": [
                "A. Provincial Congress Organisation",
                "B. Assam Congress Association",
                "C. Assam Jatiya MahaSabha",
                "D. Assam Sahitya Sabha"
            ],
            "answer": "A. Provincial Congress Organisation"
        },
        {
            "question": "'Asom Chatra Sanmilan' was formed on",
            "options": [
                "A. November 25, 1917",
                "B. December 25, 1921",
                "C. December 25, 1916",
                "D. November 25, 1933"
            ],
            "answer": "C. December 25, 1916"
        },
        {
            "question": "The first session of ‗Asom Chatra Sanmilan‘ was held in",
            "options": [
                "A. Guwahati",
                "B. Tezpur",
                "C. Jorhat",
                "D. Dibrugarh"
            ],
            "answer": "A. Guwahati"
        },
        {
            "question": "Who was the first president of the first session of ‗Asom Chatra Sanmilan‘?",
            "options": [
                "A. Lakshminath Bezbaruah",
                "B. Anandaram Dhekial Phukan",
                "C. Anandachandra Agarwala",
                "D. Chandrakumar Agarwala"
            ],
            "answer": "A. Lakshminath Bezbaruah"
        },
        {
            "question": "The Asam Sahitya Sabha was founded in",
            "options": [
                "A. July 1917",
                "B. January 1917",
                "C. December 1917",
                "D. December 1929"
            ],
            "answer": "C. December 1917"
        },
        {
            "question": "First conference of Asam Sahitya Sabha was held at",
            "options": [
                "A. Guwahati",
                "B. Tezpur",
                "C. Jorhat",
                "D. Sivasagar"
            ],
            "answer": "D. Sivasagar"
        },
        {
            "question": "Who was the first president of Asam Sahitya Sabha?",
            "options": [
                "A. Tarun Ram Phukan",
                "B. Kuladhar Chaliha",
                "C. Padmanath Gohain Baruah",
                "D. Laxminath Bezbaruah"
            ],
            "answer": "C. Padmanath Gohain Baruah"
        },
        {
            "question": "The headquarter of Assam Sahitya Sabha is situated at",
            "options": [
                "A. Jorhat",
                "B. Sivasagar",
                "C. Guwahati",
                "D. Tinsukia"
            ],
            "answer": "A. Jorhat"
        },
        {
            "question": "When was the dyarchy system introduced in Assam Province?",
            "options": [
                "A. 1917",
                "B. 1918",
                "C. 1919",
                "D. 1920"
            ],
            "answer": "C. 1919"
        },
        {
            "question": "Who was a minister of Assam under the dyarchy system?",
            "options": [
                "A. Promode Chandra Dutta",
                "B. Gopinath Bordoloi",
                "C. Fakhruddin Ali Ahmed",
                "D. Bishnu ram Medhi"
            ],
            "answer": "A. Promode Chandra Dutta"
        },
        {
            "question": "Who was NOT an Indian minister under the dyarchy scheme?",
            "options": [
                "A. Rai Bahadur Promode Chandra Dutta",
                "B. Sir Syed Muhammad Saadulla",
                "C. Gopinath Bordoloi",
                "D. Bishnuram Medhi"
            ],
            "answer": "C. Gopinath Bordoloi"
        },
        {
            "question": "The first-ever delegation of Assamese leaders to the 1921 Nagpur session of the Indian National Congress was led by",
            "options": [
                "A. Ambikagiri Raichoudhari",
                "B. Kuladhar Chaliha",
                "C. Chandranath Sharma",
                "D. Nabin Chandra Bardoloi"
            ],
            "answer": "D. Nabin Chandra Bordoloi"
        },
        {
            "question": "Assam was given the status of a province under a Governor in the year",
            "options": [
                "A. 1912",
                "B. 1921",
                "C. 1826",
                "D. 1947"
            ],
            "answer": "B. 1921"
        },
        {
            "question": "When did Mahatma Gandhi first visit Assam?",
            "options": [
                "A. 1826",
                "B. 1842",
                "C. 1845",
                "D. 1921"
            ],
            "answer": "D. 1921 (4 times Gandhi visited Assam - 1921, 1926, 1934 and in 1946)"
        },
        {
            "question": "Where and when did Gandhiji first visit Assam?",
            "options": [
                "A. Golakganj on 18th August 1921",
                "B. Karimganj on 18th August 1921",
                "C. Rangia on 18th August 1921",
                "D. Pandu on 18th August 1921"
            ],
            "answer": "A. Golakganj on 18th August 1921"
        },
        {
            "question": "In which of the following years, Mahatma Gandhi didn't visit Assam?",
            "options": [
                "A. 1921",
                "B. 1926",
                "C. 1929",
                "D. 1934"
            ],
            "answer": "C. 1929"
        },
        {
            "question": "When did the Assam Association merge with the Assam Provincial Congress Committee? Or - When was Assam Provincial Congress Committee formed?",
            "options": [
                "A. 1905",
                "B. 1911",
                "C. 1919",
                "D. 1921"
            ],
            "answer": "D. 1921"
        },
        {
            "question": "Who was the first selected president of the Assam Pradesh Congress Committee?",
            "options": [
                "A. Tarun Ram Phukan",
                "B. Chabilal Upadhyaya",
                "C. Nabin Chandra Bordoloi",
                "D. Bimala Prasad Chaliha"
            ],
            "answer": "B. Chabilal Upadhyaya"
        },
        {
            "question": "Who was the first elected president of the Assam Pradesh Congress Committee?",
            "options": [
                "A. Tarun Ram Phukan",
                "B. Kuladhar Chaliha",
                "C. Nabin Chandra Bordoloi",
                "D. Bimala Prasad Chaliha"
            ],
            "answer": "B. Kuladhar Chaliha"
        },
        {
            "question": "First woman in Assam to be killed for participating in the Non-cooperation Movement was",
            "options": [
                "A. Mongri",
                "B. Pushpalata Das",
                "C. Bhanuati Talukdar",
                "D. Chandraprabha Saikiani"
            ],
            "answer": "A. Mongri"
        },
        {
            "question": "Who was the first woman martyr in the history of Assam's freedom struggle?",
            "options": [
                "A. Kanakalata Baruah",
                "B. Bhogeswari Phukanani",
                "C. Numli Nath",
                "D. Malati Mem"
            ],
            "answer": "D. Malati Mem (Mongri)"
        },
        {
            "question": "Who was Malati Mem alias Mungri?",
            "options": [
                "A. First woman graduate of Assam.",
                "B. First woman I.A.S. of Assam.",
                "C. First woman martyr of Assam.",
                "D. First woman representative of Assam to the Legislative council of the state."
            ],
            "answer": "C. First woman martyr of Assam."
        },
        {
            "question": "Who among the following was called 'Sarojini of Assam' by Gandhiji?",
            "options": [
                "A. Chandraprava Saikiani",
                "B. Bhugeswari Phukanani",
                "C. Bhanumati Talukdar",
                "D. Pushpalata Das"
            ],
            "answer": "C. Bhanumati Talukdar"
        },
        {
            "question": "Who was popularly known as ―Voluntariny Baai‖?",
            "options": [
                "A. Chandraprava Saikiani",
                "B. Bhugeswari Phukanani",
                "C. Bhanumati Talukdar",
                "D. Pushpalata Das"
            ],
            "answer": "C. Bhanumati Talukdar"
        },
        {
            "question": "Who had conferred Gopinath Bordoloi with the title 'Lokapriya'?",
            "options": [
                "A. Jayram Das Daulatram",
                "B. Saiyid Fazal Ali",
                "C. Vishnu Sahay",
                "D. Braj Kumar Nehru"
            ],
            "answer": "A. Jayram Das Daulatram"
        },
        {
            "question": "In which year Gopinath Bordoloi was arrested for taking part in the freedom movement?",
            "options": [
                "A. 1915",
                "B. 1918",
                "C. 1920",
                "D. 1922"
            ],
            "answer": "D. 1922"
        },
        {
            "question": "When was the Swaraj Party formed in Assam and who took the leadership?",
            "options": [
                "A. 26th September 1921 by Sir Sayed Sadullah.",
                "B. 29th January 1922 by Gopinath Bordoloi.",
                "C. 25th July 1923 by Tarun Ram Phukan.",
                "D. 15th August 1947 by Bishnu Ram Medhi."
            ],
            "answer": "C. 25th July 1923 by Tarun Ram Phukan."
        },
        {
            "question": "Who was the chief/President of the Swaraj Party in Assam?",
            "options": [
                "A. Tarun Ram Phukan",
                "B. Liladhar Baruah",
                "C. Manik Chandra Baruah",
                "D. Chandradhar Baruah"
            ],
            "answer": "A. Tarun Ram Phukan"
        },
        {
            "question": "Who among the following was the first leader from Assam to be elected to the Congress Working Committee?",
            "options": [
                "A. MD. Tayebulla",
                "B. Tarun Ram Phukan",
                "C. Kuladhar Chaliha",
                "D. Bhola Nath Barua"
            ],
            "answer": "B. Tarun Ram Phukan"
        },
        {
            "question": "In Guwahati, the 41st INC session was held at",
            "options": [
                "A. Pandav Nagar (Pandu)",
                "B. Jawahar Nagar",
                "C. Jalukabri",
                "D. Dispur"
            ],
            "answer": "A. Pandav Nagar (Pandu)"
        },
        {
            "question": "Assam hosted the Indian National Congress session for the first time at Pandu in the year",
            "options": [
                "A. 1921",
                "B. 1926",
                "C. 1930",
                "D. 1932"
            ],
            "answer": "B. 1926"
        },
        {
            "question": "The opening song of the Pandu Session of the Indian National Congress 'Aji Bondo Ki Sondere' was composed by",
            "options": [
                "A. Bhupen Hazarika",
                "B. Tarunnam Phukne",
                "C. Laxminath Bezbaruah",
                "D. Ambikagiri Rai Chaudhary"
            ],
            "answer": "D. Ambikagiri Rai Chaudhary"
        },
        {
            "question": "Who founded the ―Sangrakshini Sabha‖?",
            "options": [
                "A. Bhupen Hazarika",
                "B. Tarunnam Phukne",
                "C. Laxminath Bezbaruah",
                "D. Ambikagiri Rai Chaudhary"
            ],
            "answer": "D. Ambikagiri Rai Chaudhary"
        },
        {
            "question": "In which year ―O Mor Aponar Desh‖ was officially adopted as the state song of Assam?",
            "options": [
                "A. 1927",
                "B. 1932",
                "C. 1937",
                "D. 1929"
            ],
            "answer": "A. 1927"
        },
        {
            "question": "Who among the following from Assam joined the famous Dandi march?",
            "options": [
                "A. Liladhar Barua",
                "B. Nabin Ch. Bordoloi",
                "C. Tarun Ram Phukan",
                "D. Kuladhar Chaliha"
            ],
            "answer": "A. Liladhar Barua"
        },
        {
            "question": "Who organized ―Mrityu Bahini‖ in Assam for fighting against the British during India‘s independence movement?",
            "options": [
                "A. Chandraprabha Saikiani",
                "B. Kanaklata Barua",
                "C. Pushpalata Das",
                "D. Padumi Nath"
            ],
            "answer": "C. Pushpalata Das"
        },
        {
            "question": "Which one is the only Assamese who represented India in the Round Table Conference held at London in 1930?",
            "options": [
                "A. Chandradhar Barua",
                "B. Tarun Ram Phukan",
                "C. Gopinath Bordoloi",
                "D. Krishna Nath Sarmah"
            ],
            "answer": "A. Chandradhar Barua"
        },
        {
            "question": "All Assam Ryot Sabha was formed in the year",
            "options": [
                "A. 1933",
                "B. 1935",
                "C. 1945",
                "D. 1947"
            ],
            "answer": "A. 1933"
        },
        {
            "question": "All Assam Ryot Sabha was formed in 1933 under he guidance of",
            "options": [
                "A. Nabin Chandra Bordoloi",
                "B. Gopinath Bardoloi",
                "C. Kuladhar Chaliha",
                "D. Thanuram Phukan"
            ],
            "answer": "A. Nabin Chandra Bardoloi"
        },
        {
            "question": "Provincial Self-Autonomy was introduced to Assam in the year",
            "options": [
                "A. 1935",
                "B. 1937",
                "C. 1940",
                "D. 1941"
            ],
            "answer": "A. 1935"
        },
        {
            "question": "Which of the following act made Assam an autonomous province?",
            "options": [
                "A. 1935 Government of India Act.",
                "B. Charter Act. 1853",
                "C. Indian Council Act. (1861)",
                "D. Rowlatt Act (1919)"
            ],
            "answer": "A. 1935 Government of India Act."
        },
        {
            "question": "In which year Sir Shadulla's ministry was formed?",
            "options": [
                "A. 1951",
                "B. 1950",
                "C. 1937",
                "D. 1947"
            ],
            "answer": "C. 1937"
        },
        {
            "question": "Who was the Chief Minister of Assam during the Japanese invasion in India?",
            "options": [
                "A. Sir Syed Muhammad Saadulla",
                "B. Gopinath Bordoloi",
                "C. Governor was ruling at that time",
                "D. Bishnuram Medhi"
            ],
            "answer": "A. Sir Syed Muhammad Saadulla"
        },
        {
            "question": "The Assam Public Service Commission came into effect on:",
            "options": [
                "A. 1st March, 1937",
                "B. 1st March, 1950",
                "C. 1st April, 1937",
                "D. 1st April, 1950"
            ],
            "answer": "C. 1st April, 1937"
        },
        {
            "question": "The Tribal League in Assam was founded in the year",
            "options": [
                "A. 1921",
                "B. 1924",
                "C. 1929",
                "D. 1937"
            ],
            "answer": "D. 1937"
        },
        {
            "question": "Who was the only representative from Assam as well as Northeast India to the drafting committee of the Indian constitution?",
            "options": [
                "A. Syed Muhammad Saadulla",
                "B. Bishnuram Medhi",
                "C. Gopinath Bordoloi",
                "D. Liladhar Baruah"
            ],
            "answer": "A. Syed Muhammad Saadulla"
        },
        {
            "question": "Who was a cabinet minister in the Gopinath Bordoloi‘s Ministry in 1938?",
            "options": [
                "A. Sir Syed Muhammad Saadulla",
                "B. Rai Bahadur Promode Chandra Dutta",
                "C. Fakhruddin Ali Ahmed",
                "D. Bishnuram Medhi"
            ],
            "answer": "C. Fakhruddin Ali Ahmed"
        },
        {
            "question": "Kanaklata Barua became the first martyr of which one of the following national movements?",
            "options": [
                "A. Non-Cooperation Movement",
                "B. Civil Disobedience Movement",
                "C. Quit India Movement",
                "D. Swadeshi Movement"
            ],
            "answer": "C. Quit India Movement (1942)"
        },
        {
            "question": "During the Quit India Movement, Kanaklata Barua and Mukunda Kakati were shot dead by the British Police at",
            "options": [
                "A. Gohpur",
                "B. Tezpur",
                "C. Sotiya",
                "D. Nagaon"
            ],
            "answer": "A. Gohpur"
        },
        {
            "question": "Kushal Konwar was hanged in the charge of:",
            "options": [
                "A. Non-cooperation movement & Satyagraha in Golaghat.",
                "B. Quit India Movement.",
                "C. Conspiracy & train derailment near Sarupathar, Golaghat.",
                "D. Sipoy Mutiny."
            ],
            "answer": "C. Conspiracy & train derailment near Sarupathar, Golaghat."
        },
        {
            "question": "Who was the only martyr in India to be hanged during the Quit India movement?",
            "options": [
                "A. Kanaklata Barua",
                "B. Mukunda Kakati",
                "C. Bhagat Singh",
                "D. Kushal Konwar"
            ],
            "answer": "D. Kushal Konwar"
        },
        {
            "question": "\"He alone can be a true satyagrahi who knows the art of living and dying.\" The above statement of Mahatma Gandhi is related to:",
            "options": [
                "A. Kanaklata Barua",
                "B. Mukunda Kakati",
                "C. Maniram Dewan",
                "D. Kushal Konwar"
            ],
            "answer": "D. Kushal Konwar"
        },
        {
            "question": "Bhogeswari Phukanani died during the",
            "options": [
                "E. Non-Cooperation Movement",
                "F. Civil Disobedience Movement",
                "G. Quit India Movement",
                "H. Swadeshi Movement"
            ],
            "answer": "G. Quit India Movement"
        },
        {
            "question": "Who was the governor of Assam during the Quit India Movement?",
            "options": [
                "A. Robert Neil Reid",
                "B. Sir Akbar Hydari",
                "C. Andrew Gourlay Clow",
                "D. None of these"
            ],
            "answer": "C. Andrew Gourlay Clow"
        },
        {
            "question": "The Satradhikar who played an active role in social reform and freedom movement of India was",
            "options": [
                "A. Auniatiya Satradhikar (Pitambar Dev Goswami)",
                "B. Bengenatiya Satradhikar (Banamali Dev Goswami)",
                "C. Kamalabari Satradhikar (Dr. Narayan Dev Goswami)",
                "D. Dakhinpatiya Satradhikar (Ramakanta Dev Goswami)"
            ],
            "answer": "A. Auniatiya Satradhikar (Pitambar Dev Goswami)"
        },
        {
            "question": "Shanti Sena force was formed in Assam before the",
            "options": [
                "A. Civil Disobedience Movement",
                "B. Non-cooperation movement",
                "C. Khilafat Movement",
                "D. Quit India Movement"
            ],
            "answer": "D. Quit India Movement"
        },
        {
            "question": "Who among the following was the Governor of Assam at the time of India's independence?",
            "options": [
                "A. Sir Akbar Hydari",
                "B. Fakruddin Ali Ahmed",
                "C. L. P. Singh",
                "D. Tarun Ram Phukan"
            ],
            "answer": "A. Sir Akbar Hydari"
        },
        {
            "question": "Who was the last Governor of pre-independent Assam?",
            "options": [
                "A. A.C. Chatterjee",
                "B. Sir Akbar Hydari",
                "C. Mutaguchi Renya",
                "D. None of these"
            ],
            "answer": "B. Sir Akbar Hydari"
        },
        {
            "question": "In which of the following years was Sylhet transferred to East Pakistan?",
            "options": [
                "A. 1946",
                "B. 1947",
                "C. 1948",
                "D. 1950"
            ],
            "answer": "B. 1947"
        },
        {
            "question": "Which district was separated from Assam and given to Pakistan in 1947?",
            "options": [
                "A. Chittagong",
                "B. Khulna",
                "C. Sylhet",
                "D. Sholashahar"
            ],
            "answer": "C. Sylhet"
        },
        {
            "question": "Who did not belong to Jonaki Yug? (APSC Prelims 1998)",
            "options": [
                "A. Lakshminath Bezbaruah",
                "B. Chandrakumar Agarwalla",
                "C. Hemchandra Goswami",
                "D. None of the above"
            ],
            "answer": "C. Hemchandra Goswami"
        },
        {
            "question": "The first rebellion against the British rule in Assam in 1828 was led by (APSC Prelims 2000)",
            "options": [
                "A. Piyali Phukan",
                "B. Maniram Dewan",
                "C. Gomdhar Konwar",
                "D. Piyali Barua"
            ],
            "answer": "C. Gomdhar Konwar"
        },
        {
            "question": "Which district was separated from Assam and given to Pakistan? (APSC Prelims 2000)",
            "options": [
                "A. Chittagong",
                "B. Khulna",
                "C. Sylhet",
                "D. Shala Shakar"
            ],
            "answer": "C. Sylhet"
        },
        {
            "question": "Under the Mountbatten Plan, a referendum in Assam was to be held in the district of (APSC Prelims 2000, 2013)",
            "options": [
                "A. Sivasagar",
                "B. Lakhimpur",
                "C. Golaghat",
                "D. Sylhet"
            ],
            "answer": "D. Sylhet"
        },
        {
            "question": "A pioneer lady responsible for forming the ―Mrityu Bahini‖ in Assam in connection with the freedom struggle of the country as (APSC Prelims 2000)",
            "options": [
                "A. Chandraprabha Saikiani",
                "B. Pushpalata Das",
                "C. Rani Gaidinliu",
                "D. None of them"
            ],
            "answer": "B. Pushpalata Das"
        },
        {
            "question": "The ―Shanti Sena Force‖ was formed in Assam during the Independence Movement before the commencement of the (APSC Prelims 2013)",
            "options": [
                "A. Quit India Movement",
                "B. Civil Disobedience Movement",
                "C. Non-Cooperation Movement",
                "D. Ahom Association"
            ],
            "answer": "A. Quit India Movement"
        },
        {
            "question": "When was Assam Provincial Congress formed? (APSC Prelims 2013)",
            "options": [
                "A. 1920",
                "B. 1921",
                "C. 1922",
                "D. 1923"
            ],
            "answer": "B. 1921"
        },
        {
            "question": "The author of Asomiya Sahityar Buranji is (APSC Prelims 2013)",
            "options": [
                "A. Nathan Brown",
                "B. Jatindranath Duwara",
                "C. Debendranath Bezbarua",
                "D. Gunabhiram Barua"
            ],
            "answer": "C. Debendranath Bezbarua"
        },
        {
            "question": "The Assam region was separated from the Bengal Presidency in (APSC Prelims 2013)",
            "options": [
                "A. 1874",
                "B. 1889",
                "C. 1861",
                "D. 1826"
            ],
            "answer": "A. 1874"
        },
        {
            "question": "The British-made aerodrome at Barnagar, Sarbhog, was set ablaze under the leadership of Brajanath Sarma in (APSC Prelims 2013)",
            "options": [
                "A. August 1942",
                "B. August 1842",
                "C. September 1942",
                "D. August 1941"
            ],
            "answer": "A. August 1942"
        },
        {
            "question": "Who was hanged with Maniram Dewan? (APSC Prelims 2017)",
            "options": [
                "A. Dutiram Barua",
                "B. Pioli Barua",
                "C. Pioli Phukan",
                "D. Farmud Ali"
            ],
            "answer": "B. Pioli Barua"
        },
        {
            "question": "Year 1894 is related to (APSC Prelims 2017)",
            "options": [
                "A. Phulaguri Dhawa",
                "B. Rangia Revolt",
                "C. Patharughat Revolt",
                "D. None of the above"
            ],
            "answer": "C. Patharughat Revolt"
        },
        {
            "question": "1836 CE was crucial in case of Assamese language and literature because (APSC Prelims 2017)",
            "options": [
                "A. Assamese was reinstated as an official language of Assam",
                "B. Bengali was introduced as an official language of Assam",
                "C. First Assamese novel was published",
                "D. First magazine was published from Calcutta"
            ],
            "answer": "B. Bengali was introduced as an official language of Assam"
        }
    ]
}
